We can then go ahead and use these in if statements. So, if statements will only run.
If the expression is true, not if the expression is false. To define if statements,
you just type the F keyword followed by an expression that evaluates to true or false.
If you're not sure if your expression evaluates to true or false, you can pass it into bull.
So, I can say if three is less than five. And that will run because my expression is true.
If I try to do the same thing, but reverse the order, three is, um,
I wanted to ask is a five less than three. This is false. And so, this will never run.
You can use and or not all of those inside of the expression in your if statement.
So, if I have a is true and b equals false, I can say if not be.
Will this print out high or not? It will, right? Because b is false, I've now negated it in my
abstainment. You want to be mindful of if statements and truthiness. All of those same things that
we talked about earlier apply. So, if I try to say if empty list print high,
the truthiness of an empty list is false. And so, nothing is going to happen. I can put some
values in here and then that will print high. Same for zero is false. Any number, including negative
is true. And if I have a variable like this, b is empty list, I can just say if b print high.
So, um, pretty important Python syntax. I don't have to say if b is double equals to empty list
or anything like that because that what really matters is the truthiness of the expression.
So, that's a pretty important concept. Um, we want to be mindful of not using that double
equals true in our if statements. So, I don't want to say if b double equals true, I don't do this
print high. Because that's not, uh, well, it might work. That is not correct Python syntax.
We can add an all statement to our if statement and that will only run if the if statement
itself did not run. I just want to show you the syntax for that in Python. So, um, if 5 is less than
3, print high. Else goes right beneath that if statement with a colon, there's no expression for
else because else only runs if the if statement is not true. I also want to indent that.
And now my all statement is going to run. I actually have had a question on dicks.
Um, is it possible to delete a key? That's how I've been since it's a view over writing one
by wasn't sure if you could. Yes, you can delete a key from a dictionary with the del keyword.
You can also pop from a dictionary. So, let's quickly take a look at that.
Oops. I need to use curly braces. So, my dictionary now has these keys in it. And I can pass
in which one to delete. I recommend not using the syntax even though you might see it. I think
it's kind of weird. I prefer pop instead because pop also returns the value of the key that you
just deleted. And if you need to know more about pop, you can look at help on dicks.pop.
You can also provide a defaults. So, you would have like a default once a pop. That's kind of
Yeah, like the default would be what's returned by the pop. If the key is not found.
So, kind of if you don't want to take that extra step of checking for an exception,
because if I tried to delete from my dictionary a key that does not exist,
I'm going to get a key error. So, if you don't want to do any extra exception handling,
you can use pop and pass in a default. To return if that key isn't found instead of throwing an
exception. Can you have a question regarding, still a little confused about the whole equals equals.
For example, for example, I put this in the Zoom chat 3 is less than 5 equals equals to true
the value of false. Yeah, you don't want to do that because generally expressions have their own
truthiness. And so, you don't have to use that double equals to compare it to true or false. It
just happens under the hood. And you can double check that by passing an E value or an expression to bull.
So, I can say if 3 is less than 5, what's happening here is that Python is replacing this
expression with the result of this under the hood.
Okay, I think I understand why I don't have to do that, but I really understand why it
the result seems to be counter to what I believe it should be. I think there's some, I'm not 100% sure
because generally like I know it's best practice not to do this and so I don't. I think there's a
weird order of operations thing happening here where this is getting evaluated first and this is
getting evaluated second. I think that's why it's returning false. So, it's saying is 5 equals to true
false is 3 less than false. Remember, false is actually a number. False is 0 and Python. So, then
this expression becomes is 3 less than 0 which is false. So, you end up with some weird subtle bugs.